בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. All right, so today's דף daf, *daf* is
ט״ז *Tet-Zayin*, but we pick up on ט״ו עמוד ב׳ *Tet-Vav amud
bet*. And we are where are we? It is okay, בחצר בית
המלך הפנימית *Bechatzer beit hamelech hapnimiyit*. Right, we
are the first wide line. Yes, the first, the widest of the
lines. בחצר בית המלך הפנימית *Bechatzer beit hamelech hapnimiyit*, continuing to interpret
the פסוקים p'sukim. *psukim* in the מגילה Megillah, *Megillah*. And so Esther
comes into the innermost chamber of the king's house. אמר רבי לוי
*Amar Rabbi Levi*, כיון שהגיעה לבית הצלמים *keivan shehigi'a leveit hatzelamim*, when
she came to the house of idols, the chamber of idols, presumably
now we're assuming there's a chamber of idols leading up to the
innermost chamber, נסתלקה הימנה שכינה
*nistalka heimena Shechinah*, the שכינה *Shechinah* departed from her because she had,
right, because it says when she cloaked herself with מלכות *malchut*, that
meant רוח הקודש *Ruach HaKodesh*, and now the שכינה *Shechinah* is departing.
אמרה *Amra*, she said, אלי אלי למה עזבתני *Eli Eli lama azavtani*,
my God, my God, why have You abandoned me? And this is
from the פרק *perek* in תהילים *Tehillim* that is איילת השחר *Ayelet
HaShachar*, which is interpreted to be about Esther. שמא אתה דן על
שוגג כמזיד ועל אונס כרצון *shema ata dan al shogeg kemezid ve'al
oness keratzon*, maybe You are judging the inadvertent like the willing and
like the intentional and the one who is forced like that who
is willing. Now, what does this mean? So this seems to be
going back to the earlier מדרש midrash *Midrash*, which is that Esther
said כאשר אבדתי אבדתי *ka'asher avadti avadti*, that now she is willingly
going to appease אחשורוש Achashveirosh, *Achashverosh*, or the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* feeds
in that also a seducing of אחשורוש Achashveirosh. *Achashverosh* or an approaching
him also for sexual matters, and that now she is willingly having
sex with him and sleeping with him, which will make her forbidden
to Mordechai. So here Esther is saying but I'm אונס *oness*, even
if I'm doing it willingly, the larger context is one in which
I don't have a choice because I'm doing it for the sake
of saving כלל ישראל *Klall Yisrael*. So that raises an interesting question
within this issue about was it permissible for her to do this
or not? Was she considered an אונס *oness* or not? So if
you look at רש״י *Rashi*, רש״י *Rashi* says, this is why I
was delaying discussing this from yesterday, רש״י *Rashi* says, על
אונס *al oness*, it's about ten lines down in the narrow lines
on the right-hand column, left word on the line, or first word
is the word אונס *oness*. אף על פי שאני באה אליו מאלי
אונס הוא *Af al pi she'ani ba'ah elav me'elai oness hu*, even
though I'm choosing to do it, the larger context is that I
have no choice or that I'm doing it out of necessity. So
I should just mention there's an interesting question
about whether Esther was allowed to do this or not. Right, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks about אסתר Ester, בפרהסיא הוי *Esther befarhesya havei*
and so on. So okay, let's say that she was allowed. There's
a whole question within already that issue about גילוי עריות *giluy arayot*,
was it יהרג ואל יעבור *yehareg ve'al ya'avor*, all these discussions in
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, קרקע עולם *karka olam*, whatever those issues might be. So
that's question number one of whether she was allowed to do it.
There's another fascinating question which is, was she forbidden to Mordechai afterwards?
Right, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sounds like she was because it says
כאשר אבדתי אבדתי *ka'asher avadti avadti*. But the issue is, but let's
say she was actually not only allowed, let's say she was obligated
to do this. Let's say because of פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh* or
כלל ישראל הצלת נפשות *Klall Yisrael hatzalat nefashot*, she was אונס כרצון
*oness keratzon*, she was obligated to do this. She should not have
been held liable for doing anything wrong. That was what she was
מצווה *mitzvah*, she was מצווה *metzuva* to do this. Does that necessarily
mean that she is that it doesn't impact her relationship with
Mordechai? And actually, there's a fascinating תשובה *tshuvah* about somebody who is
some man persuades a married woman, I think this was the story,
that he's אליהו הנביא *Eliyahu Hanavi* and that he has to she
has to sleep with him in order that המשיח *haMashiach* should be
their child, and she believes this guy, she sleeps with him, and
obviously he's a charlatan. And then the question is, is she permissible
to go back to her husband? So would you say, do you
determine that issue of permissibility to the husband on the question about
the the nature of the transgression? Right, so here let's say she
thought honestly thought that she was obligated to do this act, right?
So if you were to say well, she's an אומרת מותר *omeret
mutar*, she thinks it's permissible, that's not the same as מזיד *mezid*,
that's שוגג *shogeg*, maybe she's even similar to an אונס *oness*. But
the question is because the relationship to the husband, the fact that
she's forbidden to the husband is based on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
that says כי תשטה אשתו ומעלה בו מעל *ki tisteh ishto umalah
bo ma'al*. It doesn't say that she was מועל *moel* against God,
it was ומעלה בו מעל *umalah bo ma'al*. It was how she
how she impinged upon her relationship with her husband, that it was
a that it was a violation of her relationship with her husband
even if she thought from a perspective of מצווה *mitzvah* of transgression
and מצווה *mitzvah* that she was actually obligated to do the act.
So someone also so that's the question anyway and someone wanted to
raise that in terms of the Esther story, that could be that
she was obligated to do, she describes herself as אונס *oness* based
on a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* or whatever. so was
she twice or maybe she was דווקא *davka* she was supposed to
do what she did and nevertheless the מדרש Midrash *Midrash* earlier said
that כאשר אבדתי מבית אבא כך אבדתי ממך *kasher avadeti mibeis abba
kach avadeti mimcha*. But does that would that still necessarily how would
that impact in terms of her relationship with מרדכי *Mordechai*? So there
is not a clear answer on that but I at least wanted
to frame that question and here we see that she's calling it
אונס *ones*. Okay, אונס *ones*.
Question about the how broad is the category of אונס *ones*. Right,
to possibly think of אונס *ones* is you're forced to do something
against your will.
Exactly.
Right, looking at things in a larger context. Right, absolutely. So it
does raise that question as well about אונס *ones* in terms of
the larger circumstances and not only the particular choice to be doing
what you're doing. Yeah.
Aren't there הלכה *halachic* writings in recent years about whether Israeli spies
can seduce targets? Oh,
really?
Okay, interesting. Could be. So that would be relevant. Okay, so let's
keep on going. או שמא *o shema* maybe that's why you've abandoned
me. או שמא *o shema* או שקראתי לו כלב *o shekarasi lo
kelev* maybe because I called אחשורוש Achashveirosh *Achashveirosh* a dog. שנאמר she-ne'emar
*shenemar* הצילה מחרב נפשי *hatzila meicherev nafshi* again from this פסוק pasuk,
*pasuk* in תהילים *Tehillim* that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sees as referring
to אסתר Ester *Esther*. Save my soul from the sword, מיד כלב
יחידתי *miyad kelev yechidati* myself from the from the dog. So he's
abandoning you because... Right, so apparently you see that even though אחשורוש
Ahashverosh *Achashveirosh* was a רשע rasha, *rasha*, he's a king. So you
don't, you know, you have to speak with respect. חזרה וקראתו אריה
*chazra vekaraso aryeh*. So then she calls him now a lion. So
the first issue maybe God is judging her as willing. That sort
of doesn't ever response, maybe the it's sort of self-explanatory the answer.
He shouldn't be judging her as willing. But the issue about calling
a dog, that she's going to correct. שנאמר she-ne'emar *shenemar* the next
verse says הושיעני מפי אריה *hoshieini mipi aryeh*. Okay, so now she
corrected that. So she anyway thought God was abandoning her but anyway
it was apparently for a secondary reason just because of she was
in the house of idols. Now ויהי כראות המלך את אסתר Ester,
המלכה *vayehi keros hamelech es Esther hamalka*. The king sees Esther. אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan *amar Rabbi Yochanan* ג' מלאכי השרת נזדמנו
לה באותה שעה *gimmel malachei hashareis nizdamnu lah beosa sha'ah*. Three heavenly
angels appeared sort of or chanced upon her or came to her
at that time. אחד שהגביה צוארה *echad shehigbiyah tzavarah* one that lifted
up her neck so the king could see her. ויהי כראות המלך
*vayehi keros hamelech* right apparently there's a throng of people there and
he sees her. So one that lifted up her neck. ואחד שמשך
חוט של חסד עליה *ve'echad shemashach chut shel chesed aleha* one that
caused we had this idea before the the strand of charm to
be drawn over her meaning that the king saw her number one.
Number two is he you know she found favor in his eyes.
He was you know he was attracted and charmed by her. ואחד
*ve'echad* and the third שמתח את השרביט *shematach es hasharvit* caused him
to extend the the staff and to allow her to come forward.
Now וכמה *vekamah* how long did the staff extend? I presumably it
believes that it extended to reach אסתר Esther *Esther*, right? What does
the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* say? ויושט המלך לאסתר את שרביט sharvit הזהב
אשר בידו ותקרב אסתר Esther ותגע בראש השרביט *vayoshet hamelech le'Esther es
sharvit hazahav asher beyado vatikrav Esther vatiga berosh hasharvit*. So she had
to get close. But anyway presumably the מדרש Midrash *Midrash* says it's
not enough that he just lifted it up. It extended. וכמה *vekamah*
how far? אמר רבי ירמיה *amar Rabbi Yirmiyah* שתי אמות *shtei amos*
two אמות *amos* about three feet היה *hayah* that's the it was
original size והעמידו על שתים עשרה *vehe'emido al shtayim esrei* and it
grew to twelve. ואמרי לה שש עשרה *ve'amri lah shesh esrei* some
say sixteen. ואמרי לה עשרים וארבע *ve'amri lah esrim ve'arba* twenty-four. ומתניתא
תנא על ששים *umatnisa tana al shishim* in a ברייתא Braita *Braisah*
we taught sixty. Okay, now you don't you don't have to be
Freud to try to read other possible meanings into this. Okay, which
some people say is in the מגילה Megillah, *Megillah* story itself. Is
that implicit story? She right he extends the staff and she's you
know she appears and she finds favor in his eyes and whatever.
And by the way I should mention that it is interesting the
fact that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* reads the whole issue of you
know about sex into this, right? The מדרש Midrash, *Midrash* doesn't say
that she is you know sort of approaching him sexually. I mean
the מגילה *Megillah* doesn't say that but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* reads
oh if I'm going now to the מלך *melech* כאשר אבדתי אבדתי
*kasher avadeti avadeti* now I'm going to go to him and have
sex with him willingly. Who who was talking about sex? So it
already sort of put that there and
so anyway it's interesting the way it's reading it.
Also and not to be too scandalous but one does wonder why
she goes into the inner house. It's a little bit of a
reversal but we not too long ago learned about יומא *Yoma* and
about the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* going into the קודש קדשים *Kodesh
Kadashim* going into the innermost chamber and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* there
also brings up very powerful sexual imagery about that sort of sense
of intimacy and going innermost and so on. So one wonders if
that figures here as well although that would be reversing the male
and the female role. Okay I have no idea what the different
numbers are. All right. וכן את מוצא באמתה של בת פרעה *vechein
at motzei be'amasah shel bas Paroh* similarly you find by the by
the
arm of בת פרעה *bas Paroh*. The פסוק *pasuk* says ותשלח את
אמתה *vatishlach es amasah* by by משה Moshe *Moshe* she sent her
אמה *amah* which is normally understood to be her maidservant but it's
being read here also with the rabbinic אמה *amah* meaning the arm,
right, and so that she reached for her arm and her arm
extended. extended. וכן אתה מוצא בשיני רשעים,
and similarly you find by the teeth of the wicked, דכתיב d'chtiv
שיני רשעים שברת, shinei resha'im shibarta, you God have broken the teeth
of the wicked, ואמר ריש לקיש v'amar Reish Lakish אל תקרי שברת
אלא שריבבת al tikrei shibarta ela sheribavta that you have extended. It's
like it's a מדרש about עוג Og that God caused the teeth
to extend, you know, hundreds of feet. רבה בר עפרון Rabbah bar
Efron אומר omeir משום mishum רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ששמע מרבו ורבו
מרבו, sheshama meirabo v'rabo meirabo, so he had a whole tradition, מאתיים.
masayim. It's so funny, like it just seems like these are arbitrary
numbers, right, oh we have a long tradition that the שרביט extended
מאתיים אמה. masayim amah. All right, ויאמר vayomer now back to the
verse, ויאמר לה המלך לאסתר המלכה vayomer lah ha-melech l'ester ha-malkah or
מלכת אסתר המלכה. malchat Ester ha-Malkah. So the king said to אסתר,
Esther. מה בקשתך, mah bakashateich, what what do you want, what is
your desire, עד חצי המלכות ותיעש, ad chatzi ha-malchut v'teias, until half
the kingdom and it will be done. So חצי המלכות chatzi ha-malchut
up to half the kingdom, בלא כל המלכות, b'lo kol ha-malchut, not
the whole kingdom,
ולא דבר שחוצץ למלכות, v'lo davar she-chotzeitz la-malchut, not something that divides
the kingdom, ומאי ניהו בנין בית המקדש? u'mai nihu binyan Beis HaMikdash?
I won't allow for the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to return to
to be restored. So this is in the larger context, right, that
the building of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash had been had been
ceased, had been paused and אחשורוש, Achashverosh it only resumed after אחשורוש.
Ahashverosh אחשורוש Achashveirosh, is not prepared to do that.
And some places this timing is much earlier in the Persian period.
Right. Well, not much earlier. According to חז"ל, Chazal, it's only about
10 years before the בנין בית המקדש binyan Beis HaMikdash resumed in
in earnest.
Right, but the secular secular story trying to identify this is later,
perhaps.
Right, well that's true. רמב"ן Ramban also, I should mention I mentioned
this at the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, the רמב"ן Ramban understands
this to have taken place after the rebuilding started in earnest, during
like after the דריוש השני, Daryavesh HaSheini, against the גמרא. Gemara But
like that is the question: Is this before the בנין binyan or
after? The גמרא Gemara definitely understands this to be consistently like, okay,
a little bit had begun here, but it really had not begun
in earnest. Yeah.
And perhaps the different levels are significant, but what's significant is this
is a very widespread tradition. The details may have come down differently,
you know, for different people.
But the idea that it extended, right,
helps highlight that this is a very wide right,
that's true, that every that many like this understanding that it extends.
So the issue about the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is also important,
you know, because we'll see that sort of theme coming up later
as well about the power of the קרבנות korbanot and well, anyway,
we'll see the theme of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash being revisited
later on.
Yeah, where the מהרש"א Maharsha says that the difference between the 12
and 16 or whatever has to do with the number where you
start counting the number of words in the פסוק or the number
of letters.
Okay. רבה בר עפרון, Rabbah bar Efron, oh no I skipped that.
Okay, okay. יבוא המלך והמן היום אל המשתה. Yavo ha-melech v'Haman hayom
el ha-mishteh. Let the king and המן Haman come to the drinking
party that I have made for them. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מה
ראתה אסתר שזימנה את המן? mah ra'atah Ester she-zimnah et Haman? Which
is a straightforward question in the story. Now, the answer seems to
be pretty obvious, but let's take a look. Why is she trying
if she's trying to get the king to be responsive, why is
she also inviting המן Haman to the feast? So רבי אליעזר אומר
Rabbi Eliezer omeir פח טמנה לו, pach tamnah lo,
she laid traps for him, שנאמר יהי שולחנם לפניהם לפח. yehi shulchanam
lifneihem l'phach.
The table shall be for them for a trap. So like a
trap, like a פח pach is like a trap that you set
for an animal, like you know. So so the point being that
she presumably as we sort of see later, she's trying to get
the king jealous or המן Haman to do something wrong. I think
רש"י Rashi says here, where's רש"י? Rashi?
Does רש"י Rashi say? No. Okay, so let's keep on going. רבי
יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omeir מבית אביה למדה, mibeit aviha lamdah, שנאמר
אם רעב שונאך האכילהו לחם. im ra'ev sona'acha hachileihu lachem.
If your enemy is hungry, feed him bread, which basically means keep
your friends close and your enemies closer. Okay. So so she basically
wants to keep המן Haman close either because she wants to get
המן Haman in trouble and entrap המן Haman and catch him in,
you know, and be able to find something to blame him for
or just to keep an eye on him. רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi
Meir omeir כדי שלא
ייטול עצה וימרוד, kedei shelo yitol eitzah v'yimrod, also keeping the eye
on him. You know, she wants he doesn't want him to be
out of her purview, out of her sight because maybe he will
sort of get a hint that something is up and find a
way to really rebel against the king and take over or certainly
to foil her plan. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehudah omeir כדי שלא
יכירו בה שהיא יהודית, kedei shelo yakiru bah she-hi yehudit,
that people should not realize that she is Jewish because they'll say,
oh why is אסתר Esther all of a sudden going to the
king? Maybe it has something to do with המן's Haman plot. So
therefore by inviting המן, Haman, it's a, you know, it's misdirection. People
don't realize that this is that she's trying to, you know, to
intercede about the about the whole plot, about the edict of המן.
Haman. רבי נחמיה אומר Rabbi Nechemya omeir כדי שלא יאמרו ישראל אחות
יש לנו בבית המלך, kedei shelo yomru Yisrael achot yesh lanu b'veit
ha-melech, that the Jewish people shouldn't say, ah we don't have to
worry, we've got you know our sister is there in the king's
house, ויסיחו דעתם מן הרחמים v'yasichu da'atam min ha-rachamim and they'll no
longer feel the need to pray to God. So therefore, you know,
you want to keep the Jews worried that המן, Haman, oh maybe
we can't fully trust אסתר, Esther she still seems to be in
cahoots with המן, Haman, she's inviting המן Haman as well, which is
a fascinating sort of religious point here, making sure that God remains
in the picture, even though God isn't clearly in the picture in
the whole מגילה, but here assigning it that she's doing it to
keep God in the picture. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer כדי
שלא יהא מצוי לה בכל עת. kedei shelo yehei matzui lah bechol
eit. What? They were fasting. That is true, presumably with a religious
context. Okay, so in order that he should always be available to
her, and רשי, Rashi, yeah this was the רשי Rashi I was
thinking about, top רשי Rashi on the left hand side, אולי תוכל
להכשילו בשום דבר לפני המלך ulai tuchal lehachshilo beshum davar lifnei hamelech
because if המן Haman is always around, maybe she could find some
way to get him in trouble, which seemed to have been the
first point about laying a trap. Okay,
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer אולי ירגיש
המקום ויעשה לנו נס, ulai yargish HaMakom veya'aseh lanu nes, maybe God
will realize, oh my God, look how bad things are, sort of
like the reverse, like the Jewish people will realize things are not,
you know, things are a bit of a trouble. אסתר Esther, seems
to be together with המן. Haman. God will sort of see, oh
my God, look at this, אסתר Esther and אחשורוש Achashveirosh and המן,
Haman, and God will act. Of course that's very anthropomorphic, right? That,
you know, first of all God knows what it's all about, but
number two is that like, you know, but it gets to the
whole larger question about prayer, right? I mean, and getting God to
look down upon us. How do you really make theological sense of
all of that? In a way, we just finished מסכת תענית, Masechet
Ta'anit, one way of understanding the fasting is saying God, look how
miserable we are, have compassion on us. So God needs you to
act miserable for God to realize how miserable you are? So it
does touch on a similar theological point. If you look at רשי,
Rashi, ירגיש הקדוש ברוך הוא שאף אני מקרבת שונאיהם של ישראל. yargish
HaKadosh Baruch Hu she'af ani mekarevet soneihem shel Yisrael. God will feel
look how I've had to lower myself that I have to, you
know, sort of curry favor with המן. Haman. אי נמי ירגיש שאני
צריכה להחניף רשע זה ויזלזל בכבודי. ee nami yargish she'ani tzricha lehachanif
rasha zeh veyizalzel bichvodi. Oh so what was the first one? The
second one is that I have to,
I'm bringing my enemies here, so You too can bring those that,
you know, like the Jews that maybe haven't been so, maybe, maybe.
Okay, anyway, but it is a very funny point that, you know,
you need God to recognize it.
Okay, so where were we? רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר אסביר לו
פנים. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer asbir lo fanim. רבי יהושע בן
קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says let me explain it, which is
interesting, like the אסביר לו פנים asbir lo fanim is like he's
saying like I'm going to give you a better explanation. To המן?
Haman? No, no, no. אסביר לו פנים. asbir lo fanim. Today, here's
the reason: כדי שיקנא הוא והיא. kedei sheyekaneh hu vehi. That's fascinating.
He wanted the king to think that he and that she and
המן Haman were having an affair and she was willing to sacrifice
herself in order to get המן Haman out of the picture. Okay,
so שיקנא הוא והיא. sheyekaneh hu vehi. That's an interesting twist. So
it is about the king being jealous, but in a willing to
sacrifice
herself. רבן גמליאל אומר מלך הפכפכן היה, Rabban Gamliel omer melech hapachpachan
haya, I can't pronounce it, הפכפכן. hapachpachan. He was a, what would
you say? Mercurial king. He constantly, or he was always reversing himself.
So, you know, and like, you know, what?
Flip-flopper. Right, it has that nice alliteration
too. הפכפכן, hapachpachan, flip-flopper. So he's a flip-flopper. So, you know, he
one day he'll listen to המן, Haman, the next day he'll listen
to אסתר. Esther So אסתר Esther. figured I gotta get him when
I can get, what?
Everybody in the same room.
I gotta get everybody in the same room and get maybe המן
Haman killed at that moment because if I get him to agree
to me at one time and המן Haman isn't there, next time
המן Haman will be there and he'll reverse to get the king
to reverse. So better get המן Haman there, get the king, if
I can catch him at the right moment, I'll just seal the
deal. Okay, where were
we? אמר רבן גמליאל עדיין צריכין אנו למודעי. Amar Rabban Gamliel adayin
tzerichin anu laModai. We still need the למודעי, laModai, which is רבי
אלעזר המודעי, Rabbi Eleazar HaModai, who would often be, you know,
speak about
אגדתא Aggadata issues. דתניא רבי אלעזר המודעי אומר קנאתו במלך קנאתו בשרים.
Detanya Rabbi Eleazar HaModai omer kinato bamelech kinato basarim. Wanted to get
המן, Haman, get the king jealous of המן, Haman, and
the other princes, other officers jealous of המן. Haman. So what is
he adding? I mean we already said to get the king jealous.
So he's adding קנאתו בשרים. kinato basarim. And the מהרשא Maharsha explains
that what רבי אלעזר המודעי Rabbi Eleazar HaModai is adding that is
not in any of the earlier answers is why did she only
invite המן Haman and not invite anyone else. Fair. Yeah, the affair
thing also makes sense. If you invite המן Haman and other people,
then it doesn't get the king worried that there's something specific between
אסתר and
המן.
Haman. Correct. Also because whose idea was it to hang
המן? Haman? חרבונה. Harvona.
So you say it helps to get other people in the room.
What are you saying?
She she did, she's inducing חרבונה Harvona and jealousy.
Oh, I see. I don't know if חרבונה Harvona was as much
jealous as an opportunist. I think חרבונה Harvona was more of the
opportunist than jealous, but okay, anyway. All right, that's what he's adding.
He's adding that you gotta get other people also jealous of המן.
Haman. רבא אמר לפני שבר גאון. Rava amar lifnei shever ga'on. רבא
Rava says, you know, before the, you know, what is it? Haughtiness
before the, no what's the phrase? Pride comes before the fall, right.
So of course that doesn't really explain what motivated אסתר, meaning there's
like a moral message here, but that's not exactly, maybe she was
going to get him haughty and that'll, you know, I don't know,
anyway. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, Abaye veRava d'amri tarveihu, Abaye and Rava
both say בהמן, beHaman,
in other words before haughtiness before the fall, so he's being invited
there.
I understand, but it's like normally that's a moral point as opposed
to by getting him haughty that'll make him fall, maybe
he'll say something he shouldn't, maybe.
Okay, maybe. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, Abaye veRava d'amri tarveihu, Abaye and
Rava both say בחומם אשית משתיהם, bechumam ashit mishtehem, in their heat
I will place their drinking party, which basically in the context of
that verse means that people's enemies' downfalls come through, you know, as
a result of the sort of drinking too much wine and being
indulging in this way.
Okay. אשכחיה רבה בר אבוה לאליהו, Ashkechei Rabba bar Avuha l'Eliyahu, Rabba
bar Avuha found Eliyahu. אמר ליה כמאן חזיא אסתר ועבדא הכי, Amar
lei keman chazya Esther ve'avda hachi, so according to who did Esther
see and do this? Like you know everybody's trying to figure this
out, so Eliyahu maybe you can tell us what was motivating Esther.
אמר ליה ככולהו תנאי וככולהו אמוראי, Amar lei kechulhu tana'ei vechechulhu amora'ei,
all of them are true, all of those were her motivations. I
don't think any of them were like contradictory one another, so all
of them were true. Alright, anyway, it's interesting, right? Because there really,
this is like the one part I think which is most about
just really trying to understand the story, right? I mean most of
the other things is a little bit more fanciful, I mean somewhat
like מלך טיפש או מלך רשע melech tipesh o melech rasha is
I think trying to get at like a real, you know, like
a question of really interpreting the story on its own terms, like
what, you know, and which is the question, right? Was אחשורוש Achashveirosh,
you know really wanted to get rid of the Jews, was he
just somebody that was easily manipulated, did he make it look like
he could be manipulated? Right, anyway, so this also like what was
motivating
is and a lot of these reasons, it's not necessarily, I mean
Michael says that I also think that normally we tend to think
the reason is to get the king jealous, but that's to a
certain degree is influenced by the end of the story where המן
הוא נופל על המיטה אשר אסתר עליה, Haman hu nofel al hamita
asher Esther aleiha, right, so things worked out that way, but does
that necessarily mean that that was the motivation to begin with why
to invite Haman? To say like she wanted to keep her eye
on Haman, that's not such an unreasonable explanation, you know? Anyway, or
like you know or he was a flip-flopper, all of these you
know a lot of these explanations are very reasonable.
Alright, ויספר להם המן את כבוד עושרו ורוב בניו, Vayisaper lahem Haman
et kevod oshro verov banav, now Haman went and told his friends
and his family his great wealth and the myriad of his sons.
וכמה רוב בניו, Vechama rov banav, and how many sons did he
have? אמר רב ל׳, Amar Rav lamed, thirty. עשרה מתו, Asara metu,
ten died in the war, ועשרה נתלו, ve'asara nitlu, a different ten
were hanged, ועשרה מחזרים על הפתחים, ve'asara mechazrim al hapetachim, and ten
afterwards are going around begging for bread because they have been impoverished,
presumably like like you know it's it's the idea like suffering, you
know death is immediate, so the fact that there's also a sense
of ongoing suffering is also part of of his fate. ורבנן אמרי
אותן שמחזירים על הפתחים שבעים הוויה, Verabanan amri otan shemechazrim al hapetachim
shivim havya, now there were seventy that afterwards were impoverished and had
to go beg. דכתיב שבעים בלחם נשכרו, Dechtiv seve'im balechem niskaru, those
that are sated with bread you know have rented themselves out. אל
תקרי שבעים אלא שבעים, Al tikri seve'im ela shiv'im, they were seventy
and now they are like hiring themselves out for bread. ורמי בר
אבא אמר כולם מאתים ושמנה הוו, Verami bar Abba amar kulam matayim
ushmonah havu, there were
208, שנאמר ורוב בניו, shene'emar verov banav, and the rov of his
sons, ורוב בגימטריא מאתים וארבעה עשר הוו, verov begematriya matayim ve'arba'ah asar
havu, so and rov in gematria is 214 and oh I'm sorry
it's 214 not 208, right, it's 214 not 208 because if you
get the ו-ר-ו-ב, vav resh vav bet, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
ורוב כתיב, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak verov ktiv, it's written without
the middle vav, so it's only 208 not 214. Alright. בלילה ההוא
נדדה שנת המלך, Balaylah hahu nadeda shenat hamelech, in that night the
king's sleep was disturbed or was unsettled. אמר רבי תנחום נדדה שנת
מלכו של עולם, Amar Rabbi Tanchum nadeda shenat malko shel olam, God's
sleep was disturbed and therefore God now has to intervene and act,
which ties into the other story that you know Esther did it
so God would look. It's also why when we read the מגילה,
we read it you know in the different טראפ trapp to indicate
to reflect this מדרש that we're talking about sort of God.
ורבנן אמרי נדדו עליונים נדדו תחתונים, Verabanan amri nadedo elyonim nadedo tachtonim,
the upper realms and the lower realms were all bestirred in order
to you know make something happen. רבא אמר שנת המלך אחשורוש ממש,
Rava amar shenat hamelech Achashverosh mamash, no it means the king Achashverosh
and now Rava's going to give an also like a sort of
a psychological insight into what's going on here similar to the earlier
discussion of what motivated Esther. נפלה מילתא בדעתיה, Nafla milta bedateih, something
you know sort of fell in his mind, meaning something started bothering
him, you know a thought pops in his head. אמר מאי דקא
מכרה אסתר להמן, Amar mai deka machra Esther leHaman, what's going on
here that Esther invited Haman, what's that about? Right? He got very
disturbed that night. דילמא עצה קא שקלי עילויאי, Dilma etza ka shakli
ilvay, maybe they are like plotting against me? דהוא גברא למקטליה, Dehu
gavra lemiktleih, that man, meaning Haman here, my you know my
officer... עלוי דההוא גברא, Aluyai de-hahu gavra, thanks, I'm sorry, correct. About
me, right? They, they, thank you, they are plotting against me למקטליה
le-miktlei in order to kill him. You're right, it's in third person
but it refers to him. Right, right, right. So maybe my, my,
maybe my, my favorite minister and my queen, what are they doing
together? Maybe they're plotting against me to kill me. הדר אמר, Hadar
amar, then he said to himself, אי הכי לא הוי גברא דרחים
לי דהוי מודע לי. I hachi lo havai gavra derachim li dehavai
moda li. So if that's true that there's a plot against me
and I'm ignorant of it, that means that nobody cares for me
and loves me that would inform me of this plot. If there
is a plot, why am I ignorant of it? So הדר אמר
דילמא איכא איניש דעבד בי טיבותא ולא פרעיתיה. Hadar amar dilma ika
inish de-avad bi tivusa velo pariteih. Maybe there's somebody that once did
a good thing for me and I never actually compensated him. ומשום
הכי מימנעי אינשי ולא מגלו לי. U-mishum hachi mimnei inshi velo miglu
li. And therefore people don't want to help me out because they
see that I, people in the past, when people have helped me
out they weren't rewarded. So that's maybe why nobody here is informing
me. Right? So the biggest evidence of a conspiracy is that there's
no evidence of the conspiracy. Right?
What a conspiracy! Then why doesn't anybody tell me about it? Because
it's a good conspiracy, so nobody wants to be telling me about
it. Okay. So ויאמר המלך, Vayomer hamelech, so anyway, so it must
be that people don't feel they can tell me about these things.
So I've got to figure out if that's true. ויאמר להביא את
ספר הזכרונות דברי הימים ויהיו נקראים. Vayomer lehavi et sefer hazichronot divrei
hayamim ve-yihyu nikraim. So I said let's go and check the history
books. Let's go and see if ever somebody did something for me
and informed me of a conspiracy that I did not reward that
person. ויהיו נקראים, Ve-yihyu nikraim, and let them be read. מלמד שנקראים
מאליהם. Melamed shenikraim me-aleihem. So they sort of read themselves, okay, it
was a magic book. וימצא כתוב, Vayimatze katuv, and it was found
written. כתב מבעי ליה, Katav mibei lei, it should have been written
in the past, כתוב katuv has the sense of currently being written.
So
מלמד melamed שתוספות Tosafot דף פ''ו עמוד
א', daf pei vav amud aleph, ששמש מוחק וגבריאל כותב, she-shamash mochek
ve-Gavriel kotev, that the שמש, shamash, the attendant who was reading it,
saw what it was written about Mordechai, he didn't like the Jews,
so he was trying to erase that line about Mordechai, and Gabriel
was rewriting it as this guy was erasing it. So that's כתוב
katuv or like כותב, kotev, like it's being written right now. אמר
רבי אסי דרש רב שילא איש כפר תמרתא, Amar Rabbi Assi darash
Rav Shila ish Kefar Tamarta, so Rav Shila expounded. ומה כתב שלמטה
שלזכותן של ישראל אינו נמחק, Umah ktav she-lematah she-lizchutan shel Yisrael eino
nimchak, so if the thing below that was written in the king's
history books, which benefits the Jewish people, cannot be erased, כתב שלמעלה
לא כל שכן, ktav she-lemalah lo kol she-ken, how much more so
what is written above up in heaven, you know, that the, that
for the benefit of the Jews, that God will always be there,
make sure that they will be protected. Okay. So then the king
says what was done for Mordechai? לא נעשה עמו דבר, Lo na’asa
imo davar, nothing. אמר רבא לא מפני שאוהבים את מרדכי אלא מפני
ששונאים את המן. Amar Rava lo mipnei she-ohavim et Mordechai ela mipnei
she-sonim et Haman. This is a good line to use in other
contexts. They didn't say this to king because they were such friends
of Mordechai; they said it because they couldn't stand Haman.
So often a lot of people are motivated more from who they
hate than from who they love. My enemy's enemy is my friend,
right. Okay.
הכין
לו, Heichin lo, so Haman was standing in the king's chamber to
tell him about the עץ etz that he made for Mordechai, that
he prepared for Mordechai. So the גמרא says תנא לא הכין לו,
Tana lo heichin lo, he actually הכין לו, heichin lo, he actually
it's going to turn out that Haman had really prepared it for
himself. So reading that as ironic.
Okay.
ויעש כן
למרדכי,
Vaya’as
ken le-Mordechai, so
oh I just misread that. ויעש כן למרדכי. Vaya’as ken le-Mordechai. So
then the king says: Great idea, do this for Mordechai. אמר ליה
מנו מרדכי, Amar lei manu Mordechai, so Haman said to Ahasuerus, which
Mordechai? So אמר ליה היהודי, Amar lei hayehudi, the Jewish Mordechai. אמר
ליה סגיא מרדכי איכא ביהודאי, Amar lei sagi Mordechai ika biyehudaye, oh
there are a lot of Jewish Mordechais. Maybe you got the wrong
one. No, אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him: היושב בשער
המלך. Hayoshev beshaar hamelech. Right, right, exactly. It's the רחל בת יצחק
קטנה. Rachel bat Yitzchak Ketana. No, the one who sits in the
king's gate. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so then Haman said: You know,
סגי ליה בחד דסקרתא, sagi lei be-chad daskarta, you don't need to
do this big honor for him. You could just give him a
village, אינמי בחד נהרא, inami be-chad nahara, you give him a
river, give him something else, he doesn't need to be paraded around
on the king's horse. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so the king said:
היינו נמי הב ליה, hai nami hav lei, great idea, give him
that too. אל תפל דבר מכל אשר דברת, Al tapel davar mikol
asher dibarta, everything that you said. All right. ויקח המן את הלבוש
ואת הסוס, Vayikach Haman et halevush ve-et hasus, so Haman took the
clothes and the horse. אזל אשכחיה דיתבי רבנן קמיה. Azal ashchacheih de-yitvi
rabanan kameih. So he went to get Mordechai and he found that
the rabbinic students were sitting in front of Mordechai. Here Mordechai, right,
he was a נביא navi in the previous דף, he's also one
of the
אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedolah, so he's giving a שיעור. shiur.
So ומחוי להו הלכות קמיצה לרבנן, u-machvei lehu hilchot kmitzah lerabanan, and
he's showing the rabbis how to do קמיצה, kmitzah, right, by bringing
a מנחה. minchah. So רש''י Rashi says this is because this is
right around פסח, Pesach, right, because the fast was three days starting
on.
Okay, so where were we? הלכות קמיצה לרבנן. hilchos kmitza lerabbanan. כיון
דחזיה מרדכי דאפיק לקבליה, keivan de-chazei Mordechai de-apeik le-kivlei, so Mordechai saw
Haman was coming to greet him or to approach him. וסוסיא מיחד
בידיה, ve-suseya mechad bidei, and the horse was sort of bound in
his hand, and he was sort of leading the king's horse. מירתת,
mirtat, so he didn't know how to interpret what was about to
happen. He thought maybe now Haman was about to execute him or
something, right? Haman was coming on the authority of the king. אמר
להו לרבנן, amar lehu lerabbanan, so Mordechai said to the rabbinic students,
האי רשיעא למקטל נפשי קאתי, hai rishia lemiktal nafshi ka-ati, this wicked
person is coming to kill me. זילו מקמיה, zilu mikammei, go run
away from him, דלא תכחלו בגחלתי, di-lo tikhahlu begahaltai, because if not
you'll be burned by his hot ember. So you don't want to
get in trouble with me, go leave. בההיא שעתא נתעטף מרדכי וקם
ליה בצלותיה, be-hai sha'ata nitateif Mordechai ve-kam lei bitzalusei, and now Mordechai
saw that he was about to, he thought he was about to
be killed, so he wants to be, you know, he's praying to
God, praying to God to be saved, or at least praying that
he should be killed at the moment
of connecting to God. אתא המן ויתיב ליה קמייהו. ata Haman ve-yasiv
lei kammeihu. So Haman there comes and sits in front of them,
ואריך עד דסליק מרדכי לצלותיה, ve-arikh ad desalik Mordechai letzalusei, and he
waited until Mordechai finished his שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, you know, off
of some idea, you know, you're not supposed to interrupt שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei unless somebody's coming to kill you, right? But maybe Mordechai
felt it wasn't going to make a difference. So anyway, he got
in his שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Haman waited till he finished his
שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. אמר להו, amar lehu, so Haman said to
Mordechai, it's funny אמר להו, amar lehu, it's in plural, right? קמייהו,
kammeihu, in front of them, because they're the רבנן, rabbanan, but he
told the רבנן rabbanan to leave, so maybe the רבנן rabbanan didn't
listen to them. Anyway, it sounds like the fact that it's continuing
with the plural sounds like Mordechai tried to protect the רבנן rabbanan
but the מדרש is assuming that the רבנן rabbanan refused and stayed
by Mordechai. So he said to them, במאי עסקיתו, be-mai askiseitu, what
are you doing? What what what have you been dealing with? אמרו
ליה, amru lei, so the rabbis said to Haman, בזמן שבית המקדש
קיים מאן דמנדב מנחה מייתי מלא קומציה דסולתא ומתכפר ליה. bizman shebeis
hamikdash kayam man demenadev mincha maisei mallei kumtzei desolto umiskaper lei. At
the time of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a person could bring
even a very very humble type of an offering, a hand-breath filled
with flour and they'd be atoned for. אמר להו, amar lehu, he
said to them, אתא מלא קומציה קמחא, ata mallei kumtzei kimcha, came
the hand-breath of flour, דידכו, didchu, of yours, because you were learning
it, and presumably your learning it represents as if you've brought it,
ודחי עשרה אלפי ככרי כספא דידי, ve-dachi asara alfei kikarei kaspa didi,
and they have overridden my ten thousand talents of silver. Because presumably
the timing was you were learning this at the time
when אחשורוש Achashveirosh has switched his mind or at least, you know,
said to give this honor to Mordechai. אמר ליה, amar lei, so
now what about the
other שקלים shekalim that he did before?
Well, that's the other thing, right? Their שקלים shekalim beat out his
שקלים. shekalim. Here it's the little offering of flour. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so now Mordechai has finished his שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, so
Mordechai now gets into the conversation, and he said to him, רשע,
Rasha wicked person, עבד שקנה נכסים עבד למי ונכסים למי, eved shekanah
nechasim eved lemi unechasim lemi,
you know, going back to the earlier theme that Haman was a
slave of Mordechai. So he said, you know, what is this, your
ten thousand talents of silver? That was all my money anyway. Don't
exactly get the point here, but okay. What I do think is
interesting is, you know, this whole question of here they are in
exile and what's coming to save them. So they have Esther's fast,
right, and you have
Mordechai's צעקה, tzeaqa, but then you have sort of, you know, the
theme of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? It's the merit of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. We had the שקלים shekalim of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash preceded Haman's שקלים, shekalim, the mention of
the offering here ultimately what sort of won out. On the other
hand, you have Mordechai standing in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Right? Why
did he have to insert him standing in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
into that story? Could have just had the story about he comes
and they're learning about the laws of the קמיצה. kmitza. So I
don't know exactly the answer, but I think it's interesting, you know,
about this question that dealing with this state between the two בתי
מקדש, Batei Mikdash, I think that's, you know, also after חורבן בית
שני Churban Bayis Sheini
there's also that tension of is it ultimately that what we do
is to replicate the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or is it that
תפילה tefilla actually is powerful on its own accord, you know, with
equivalent weight to that of קרבנות? korbanos? But here I also think
the, you know, constantly evoking the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and its
power and at the same time having Mordechai being standing in שמונה
עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So I don't know how to fully unpack that,
but I think that's worth mentioning. Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to Mordechai, קום לבוש הני
מאני ורכב האי סוסיא, kum livosh hani mani verchov hai suseya,
get up, put on these clothes, ride this horse, דבעי לך מלכא,
de-ba'ei lakh malka, the king wants you. So it sounds like the
king is sort of is calling him, but it's really the king
wants you to just ride on the horse.
אמר ליה, amar lei, לא יכילנא, lo yakhilna, I can't I can't
do it. עד דאזילנא לבי בני ואשקול למזיא, ad de-aleina lebei banei
ve-ashklo le-mazaya, I first have to go to the bathhouse and get
a haircut. So like the
יוסף Yosef scene. it’s not proper respect to use the
king’s vessels, objects, the horse and the garments, הכי hachi in my
current state because remember Mordechai had been in his
sackcloth and been fasting, and presumably as we learned before, the more
serious fasts you don’t bathe, you don’t get a haircut. So I
gotta, if I’m gonna do this, I gotta get myself ready. So
שדרה אסתר, shadra Esther, so Esther sent ואסרתינו לכולו בי בני va'asartinu
le'chulu bei banei and Esther locked up all the bathhouses. Why? We’ll
see in a minute. וכולו אומני ve'chulu umane and all of the
barbers. Now אומן uman by the way is often used to refer
to a bloodletter, sometimes also it’s used to refer to a מוהל,
mohel, and here it’s used to refer to a barber. Anybody know
what the common denominator between those three professions
are? They all use knives, right, and scissors and sharp objects, and
very often they were the same person. Apparently the red and the
white thing in front of the barber was about blood, right, and
also because he was a bloodletter. So anyway, yeah.
So Mordechai is gonna have a haircut on חול המועד Chol HaMoed
during... oh my god, wow. And and in the middle of a
תענית!
ta'anit! Right. And and in the middle of the עומר. Omer. I
like that point. Absolutely. He wasn't able to have a haircut. But
does he deal with the fact that it was during ספירה? Sefirah?
All right, anyway, so the גמרא says like this. All right, let’s
move back to the גמרא. Okay, so anyway we'll see why Esther
locked all these places up.
איילי ניהו לבי בני
Aylei ihu
le'bei
banei so because now
Haman is forced to be attendant to Mordechai, because Mordechai is insisting
on this. All the barbers
and the bathhouse attendants
are off work, so now
Haman has
to be the
one to take care of this. So Haman brought Mordechai into the
bathhouse ואסחי ve'aschi and bathed Mordechai, scrubbed him, he was the one
that was attending to him. ואזל ואייתי זוזא מביתיה ve'azil ve'aysei zuza
mibeisei and he went and he had to get a scissors from
his house.
Can a non-Jew cut your hair?
Okay, good question, because maybe because the king has sort of given
this edict he felt protected. וקשקא ביה מזייא ve'kashka bei mazaya and
he was cutting Mordechai’s hair. ובהדי דקשקא ליה ve'hadi de'kashka lei
as he was cutting Mordechai’s hair, אינגד ואיסתנח, ingad ve'istnach, he like
moaned and sighed. אמר ליה אמאי קא מסתנחת, amarei lei amai ka'mistnachat,
why are you letting out such a, giving out such a sigh?
אמר ליה, amarei lei, so Haman said back to Mordechai, גברא דהוה
חשיב ליה למלכא מכולהו רברבנוהי, gavra de'hava chashiv lei le'malka mikulu ravrevanohi,
the person that was more important to the king than all of
the other ministers, השתא שוויה בלני וספרא, hashata shavei balani ve'sapara, now
I’ve been turned into a bathhouse attendant and a barber? אמר ליה,
amarei lei, so Mordechai said back to him, רשיעא, Rasha, ולאו ספרא
דכפר קרצום היית, velav sapara de'kfar kartzum hayita, you used to be
a barber in some village, you’re going back to your origins. So
all of this is of course completely showing the downfall of Haman
way before just him being executed, but how he’s completely
being brought low. תנא המן ספרא דכפר קרצום היה, Tana Haman sapara
de'kfar kartzum haya, we taught in a ברייתא Haman used to be
a barber of this village, the village of Kartsum. Okay, so he
wasn’t such a big shot to begin with. עשרים ושתים שנין Esrim
ushtayim shana for
twenty-two years. בתר דשקלינהו למזייא batar de'shaklinu le'mazaye after he cut Mordechai’s
hair, אלבשינהו למאניה, alvashinu le'maneh, he dressed him with the king’s garments.
אמר ליה amarei lei and he said to him, סק ורכב, sak
ve'rachav, now get up on the horse. אמר ליה, amarei lei, so
Mordechai said to him, לא יכילנא, lo yechilna, I can’t, I can’t
just jump up on the horse, I don’t have the
strength, דכחישנא מימי תעניתא, de'chashishachali mi'yemei ta'anita, I’m weak because of the
fasting. גחין וסליק, gachin ve'salik, so Haman had to bend down and
let himself be used as a footstool so that Mordechai could get
up on the horse. כי סליק, ki salik, as Mordechai was getting
up on the horse, בעט ביה, ba'at beih, he kicked Haman. Did
he mean when he lies down? אמר ליה, amarei lei, kick, yeah
that's what Haman is going to say, that's what you do, you
kick someone when they're down? ולאו כתיב לכו, velav kesiv lachu, isn't
it written for you בנפול אויבך אל תשמח, binfol oyvecha al tismach,
do not rejoice when your enemy falls down? אמר ליה, amarei lei,
he said back to him, הני מילי בישראל, hani mili be'Yisrael, that's
by our fellow Jew, אבל בדידך כתיב, aval bedidach kesiv, but by
you it's written ואתה על במותימו תדרוך, ve'ata al bamotaymo tidroch, you
will trample their high places. So here he's trampling the high places,
he's walking on the neck and on the head of Haman. ויקרא
לפניו, vayikra lefanav, now Haman called before him, ככה יעשה לאיש אשר
המלך חפץ ביקרו, kacha ye'aseh la'ish asher hamelach chafetz bikoro, this will
be done to the man that the king desires in his honor.
דהוה נקיט ואזיל בשבילי דבי המן, de'hava nakit ve'azil be'shvilei de'bei Haman,
when he was going and walking in the passageways, the street by
Haman's house, by the alleys by Haman's house, חזיתיה ברתיה, chazisa bartei,
so Haman's daughter saw him, דקיימא אאיגרא, de'kayma aigra, and she was
on the rooftop. סברה, savra, and she thought,
האי דרכיב אבא, hai de'rachiv avua, she made a logical inference, her
guess, she figured the guy on the horse must be her father,
must be Haman, והאי דמסגי קמיה מרדכי, ve'hai de'masig kamei Mordechai, and
the person walking in front is Mordechai, must be Mordechai. שקלה עציצא
דבית הכסא, shakla atziza de'veisa d'kasei, she took the pottery, the chamber
pot of the bathhouse. of the bathroom, right, ושדיתיה ארישא דאבוה v'shadyesei
areisha d'avuha and she threw it on the head of the father.
She had good aim, she knew she would hit the guy, the
guy in front, not the guy on the horse. So דלי עיניה,
dali einei, he lifted up his eyes, and חזת chazat I'm sorry,
she lifted up her wait. Oh, he lifted up his eyes, it's
in the masculine, but then וחזת, v'chazat, and she saw once he
lifted up his head, she saw him דאבוה הוא d'avuha hu that
it was her father. נפלה מאיגרא לארעא, nafla me'igra l'ara, she fell
from the roof to the ground ומיתה umisa and she died. והיינו
דכתיב v'hainu d'chsiv and that's what's meant by the verse, וישב מרדכי
אל שער המלך. vayashav Mordechai el shaar hamelech. והמן נדחף, v'Haman nidchaf,
it's really the end of the פסוק,
והמן נדחף אל ביתו אבל וחפוי ראש v'Haman nidchaf el beiso avel
v'chafui rosh and we're going to get to that. So אמר רב
ששת amar Rav Sheshes the first thing is we translate the first
part of that: He returned לסקו ולתעניתו. l'sako u'l'saaniso. He did not
sort of like, you know, say, 'Oh, I'm great, now everything's going
to work out for me.' He went back to what he was
doing. He didn't take for granted that it was all going to
work out and he went back to his sackcloth. והמן, v'Haman, right,
which is not at all פשט pshat of the פסוקים. p'sukim פשט
Pshat of the פסוקים p'sukim is now that Mordechai is on the
ascendancy and Mordechai is now, you know, close to the king. But
the גמרא points out he was in the שער המלך shaar hamelech
fasting, so going back to the שער המלך shaar hamelech means returning
to his fasting. והמן נדחף אל ביתו, v'Haman nidchaf el beiso, Haman
was sort of, you know, driven back to his house. אבל וחפוי
ראש, avel v'chafui rosh, mourning and with a sort of covered head.
אבל, avel, mourning על בתו al bito for his daughter, וחפוי ראש
v'chafui rosh and a covered head על שאירע לו al she'eira lo
for what happened to him. Okay, so he's embarrassed, he's ashamed. ויספר
המן לזרש אשתו ולכל אוהביו. vaysaper Haman l'Zeresh ishto u'l'chol ohavav. So
he told everybody what had happened to him. So קרי להו אוהביו
וקרי להו חכמיו. kari lehu ohavav v'kari lehu chachamav. So what are
they? Are they his friends or are they his wise men? So
אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan because another verse says ויאמרו לו
חכמיו, vayomru lo chachamav, right, אם מזרע היהודים מרדכי. im mizerah Hayehudim
Mordechai. So the גמרא picks up on the fact that when they're
telling him about how the whole story is reversing itself and Mordechai
is now going to be, you know, rise up and he'll fall
down, at this stage they're חכמיו, chachamav, they become wise. So אמר
רבי יוחנן כל האומר דבר חכמה
אפילו באומות העולם נקרא חכם. kol ha'omer davar chochma afilu b'umos ha'olam
nikra chacham. Okay, now that they're actually saying something that's wise, at
that moment they're called wise men. אם מזרע היהודים מרדכי, im mizerah
Hayehudim Mordechai, if he's Jewish, לא תוכל לו, lo tuchal lo, right,
well once he starts, once he starts rising up, right, yeah, once
you start falling down, then he's going to be victorious. So the
גמרא is a little bit bothered because although, you know, the question
is, well they knew he was Jewish beforehand. But okay, but the
point is, beforehand, you know, he was, he was going down and
you were going up. Now they're saying, 'Ah, now that you're going
down, it can't be reversed.' That's the חידוש. chiddush. But the גמרא
is a little bit bothered because it sounds like all of a
sudden they realized, 'Oh, he's Jewish, you've got a little problem on
your hands.' So let's take a look. אמרו לו, amru lo, they
said to him, אם משאר שבטים קאתי, im mish'ar shvatim ka'asi, if
he's from one of the other tribes, יכולת לו. yacholta lo. Then
you'll be able to be victorious over him. But אם מזרע, im
mizerah, the emphasis here is on the מ. mem. From a certain
strand of the Jews, then you're in trouble. ואם משבט יהודה בנימין
אפרים ומנשה, v'im mishevet Yehuda Binyamin Ephraim u'Menashe, if however he comes
from Yehuda, Binyamin, Ephraim, and Menashe, we'll see it's based on a
verse, then לא תוכל לו, lo tuchal lo, then you will not
be able to be victorious over him. Why? יהודה דכתיב ידך בעורף
אויביך. Yehuda d'chsiv yadcha b'oref oyvecha. So Yehuda would be victorious. אינך
אינך דכתיב בהו לפני אפרים ובנימן ומנשה עוררה את גבורתך, inach inach
d'chsiv behu lifnei Ephraim u'Vinyamin u'Menashe orera es g'vurascha, right, bestir your
might. Now of course besides that we just have פסוקים and we
know that Mordechai is מיוחס meyuchas both to יהודה Yehuda and בנימין,
Binyamin, right, יהודי Yehudi and ימיני Yemini etc., you also have the
whole idea of, you know, which we had before that Esther descends
from King שאול, Shaul, right, so here also, so also שאול Shaul
and you know closing the circle of שאול Shaul and עמלק Amalek
and so on, so you have that connection here with the בנימין
Binyamin as well. Yes.
We have here non-Jews who know תורה. Torah.
Well, yes. Okay, so כי נפול תפול לפניו, ki nafol tipol l'fanav,
you'll certainly fall before him. דרש רבי יהודה בר אלעאי, darash Rabbi
Yehuda bar Ilai, שתי נפילות הללו למה? shtei nefilos halalu lama? What's
נפול תפול, nafol tipol, what's the double falling? אמרו לו, amru lo,
אומה זו משולה לעפר ומשולה לכוכבים. uma zu m'shula l'afar u'm'shula l'chochavim.
So this is picking up on the theme, right? Either they'll be
way at the top or way at the bottom. So they're compared
to dust and they're compared to stars. כשהן יורדין יורדין עד עפר,
k'shehen yordin yordin ad afar, when they go down, they go down
to the dust. כשהן עולין עולין עד לכוכבים. k'shehen olin olin ad
lakochavim. So they go up to the sky. So נפול תפול, nafol
tipol, I guess means just you'll be... it doesn't feel totally explain
the double language, but okay.
Well, you'll go from the greatest of heights to the...
maybe. Okay, וסריסי המלך הגיעו. v'sarisei hamelech higiu. Now the king's eunuchs
arrived ויבהילו vayavhilu and they rushed to bring המן. Haman. מלמד שהביאוהו
בבהלה, melamed sheheviu'u b'vahala, they brought him in a state of being
rushed, which is obvious, but presumably also we're supposed to remember the
previous point, which is that he had the chamber pot, you know,
still on his head or whatever and all of that, so he's
in a disgusting state and he doesn't have a chance like Mordechai
did to bathe and to change. So that's the way he's coming
to the king's house. כי נמכרנו אני ועמי. ki nimcharnu ani v'ami.
And now she says, me and my people have been sold. כי
אין הצר שוה בנזק המלך, Ki ein hatzar shoveh b'nezek hamelech, the
enemy has no concern with the damage to the king. אמר לו,
Amar lo, so she said to אחשורוש, Achashveirosh's צר זה אינו שוה
בנזק של המלך, Tzar zeh eino shoveh b'nezek shel hamelech, he's not-
he doesn't- he's not concerned with the damage to the king. איקני
בושתי וקטלה, Iknei b'Vashti v'kaktla, meaning he is jealous of all the
good things that the king has. He was jealous of ושתי, Vashti,
he got her killed, echoing back the fact that ממוכן Memuchan was
identified with המן, Haman, right? איקני בדידי, Iknei b'didi, he's jealous of
me, ומיבעי למקטלי, Umiba'i l'mikla'i, he's trying to get me killed. So
look at this, this המן Haman is getting all your wives killed.
He's jealous of any good that you have, so again, making- making
אחשורוש Achashveirosh very jealous.
ויאמר המלך אחשורוש ויאמר לאסתר המלכה, Vayomer hamelech Achashveirosh vayomer l'Esther hamalka,
so the king said, ויאמר ויאמר למה לי Vayomer vayomer lamah li?
What do you mean he said, he said, right? ויאמר המלך אחשורוש
לאסתר המלכה. Vayomer hamelech Achashveirosh l'Esther hamalka. What's the ויאמר vayomer? So
אמר רבי אבהו בתחילה על ידי תורגמן. Amar Rabi Avahu, betchila al
yedei turgeman. First he was using a translator. כיון דאמר לה מדבי
שאול אתינא, Kivan d'amar lei mid'beish Shaul asina, once she then said
that she's Jewish, right? כי נמכרנו אני ועמי, Ki nimkarnu ani v'ami,
and she presumably now filling in the blanks said that she descends
from שאול. Shaul. So presumably she descends from a kingly house, so
she knows the foreign languages. So ויאמר לאסתר המלכה, Vayomer l'Esther hamalka,
מיד ויאמר לאסתר, miyad vayomer l'Esther, he dropped the מתורגמן. meturgeman. He
said to her directly. ותאמר אסתר איש צר ואויב המן הרע הזה.
Vatomer Esther, ish tzar v'oyev, Haman hara hazeh. This wicked המן, Haman,
an evil man, this wicked המן. Haman. So why doesn't she just
say המן? Haman? Why איש צר ואויב ish tzar v'oyev? So a
famous מדרש, אמר רבי אלעזר מלמד שהיתה מחווה כלפי אחשורוש. Amar Rabi
Elazar, melamed shehayesa mechava k'lapei Achashveirosh. So she said, who's the together?
A wicked person. And she was going to point straight to אחשורוש,
you know, you're the guy as well, at least you're complicit. סו
בא מלאך וסטר ידה כלפי המן. So ba malach v'satar yada k'lapei
Haman. So the מלאך malach came and moved her hand. איש צר
ואויב המן הרע הזה. Ish tzar v'oyev Haman hara hazeh. It's like
the משה story, right? Not exactly sure, obviously the message here- it
would have been pretty stupid for אסתר to point at אחשורוש- but
the message here is, like it's not so clear, it's not all
המן. Haman. Like you know, אחשורוש fault in all of this and
responsibility, you know, might be equal to that here of המן. Haman.
והמלך קם בחמתו, V'hamelech kam b'chamato, the king rose in his anger.
והמלך שב מגינת הביתן, V'hamelech shav miginat habitan, and then he returned
from the- from the garden of the castle. מקיש שיבה לקימה. Maki
shiva l'kima. It connects, right? The verses create a parallel between his
getting up and leaving and his returning. מה קימה בחמה, Mah kima
b'chema, the same way he got up in- in anger, fiery anger,
anger, אף שיבה בחמה, af shiva b'chema, when he returned, he hadn't
calmed down at all. He was still just as angry. So he's-
so דאזל ואת. da'azal v'at. Now why was he just as angry?
He- he went to take a walk. דאזל ואשכח למלאכי השרת, D'azal
v'ashkach l'malachei hashareis, 'cause when he went into the garden, he found
heavenly angels,
דאידמו כגברי, d'idmu k'gavrei, they appeared like- like men, דקעקרי לאילני דבוסתני,
d'ka'akri l'ilanei d'bustanei, and they were uprooting the trees of the garden,
the beautiful trees of the orchard. And אמר להו, amar lehu, he
said to these people, these- these angels who looked like people, מאי
עובדייכו, mai ovdaichu, what are you doing? You're uprooting my beautiful trees
and my orchard. אמרו ליה דפקדינן המן, Amru lei, d'fakdinan Haman, המן
Haman told us to do it!
So he got just as angry, didn't- you know, he got even
maybe more angry. Okay. את לביתיה, At l'beiseih, he returned to his
house. והמן נופל על המטה. V'Haman nofel al hamitah. And המן Haman
was falling on the bed that אסתר was there. So נופל, nofel,
נפל מיבעי ליה, nafal miba'i lei, it should say that he had
prostrated himself, not נופל nofel in the present. So אמר רבי אלעזר
מלמד שבא מלאך והפילו עליה. Amar Rabi Elazar, melamed sheba malach v'hipilo
aleiha. So the מלאך malach came and was like pushing him on
top of אסתר. He was- he was trying to sort of not,
obviously, be in that compromising position. The מלאך malach was making sure
it all worked out. אמר ווי מביתא ווי מברא. Amar, vai mibeisa
vai mibara. So אחשורוש said, woe in- from the house, woe from
the outside. Everywhere I go, I see the terrible things that המן
Haman is doing.
ויאמר המלך, Vayomer hamelech, הגם לכבוש את המלכה עמי בבית hagam lichbosh
es hamalka imi babayit? Are you trying to subdue the queen with
me here in the house? ויאמר חרבונה, Vayomer Charvona, and then חרבונה
Charvona said, right? אחד מן הסריסים, echad min hasarisim, etc. אמר רבי
אלעזר אף חרבונה רשע באותה עצה היה. Amar Rabi Elazar, af Charvona
rasha b'osah eitzah hayah. רשע חרבונה Charvona was part of the plan
to make the tree. כיון שראה לא נתקיימו העצה מיד ברח. Kivan
she'ra'ah lo niskaymu ha-atztzo, miyad barach. And as soon as he saw
that it wasn't going to work out, he ran away from המן.
Haman. Meaning אף חרבונה af Charvona was an opportunist, right? It looked
like המן Haman was on the ascendancy, he was with המן. Haman.
Now it looks like המן Haman is nothing, he switches sides. והיינו
דכתיב. V'hayinu d'chtiv. Right,
והיינו דכתיב, v'hayinu d'chtiv, so even if somebody has, you know, not
ideal motivations, it's- you know, sometimes they wind up doing the right
thing. דכתיב וישלך עליו ולא יחמול מידו ברוח יברח. D'chtiv, vayashlech alav
v'lo yachmol, miyado baroach yivrach. Okay,
he doesn't have compassion, he will run away from him.
Basically חרבונה Charvona ran away from המן Haman once he saw that
things were reversing. From המן, Haman, excuse me. וחמת המלך שככה. V'chamasan
hamelech shachacha. And the king's anger abated. שתי שכיחות הללו למה Shtei
shchichos halalu lamah? Why does it say שככה? shachacha? I guess- although
שככה, shachacha, the word is שכך, shachach, I'm not exactly sure why
it's two. But okay, is it say שככה shachacha twice anyway? Does
it say twice in the פסוק?
וחמת המלך שכך, V'chamasan hamelech shachach, right? Why is it שככה, shachacha,
maybe two כs? chaf It has an extra כ. chaf. Yeah.
שכך *shachach*, no, and ששככה *sheshachacha* it says there. שכך *shachach*, no,
the verb has ש כ כ *shin chaf chaf*. Right. כשך
*keshoch*? But that's because you drop a כף *chaf*. Anyway, alright, why
are these two שככות הללו למה *shachachot halalu lama*? אחת של מלכו
של עולם *akhat shemalkho shel olam*, one God now has calmed down,
because God was the מלך *melekh* that was upset. ואחת של אחשורוש
*veakhat shel Achashverosh*. ואמרי לה *veamre lei*, and some say, אחת של
אסתר ואחת של ושתי *akhat shel Esther veakhat shel Vashti*. The king
calmed down now from two things he was angry about. He was
angry about ושתי *Vashti* and he was angry about אסתר *Esther* and
all of them because that was what אסתר *Esther* said: המן *Haman*
is trying to get ושתי *Vashti* killed, trying to get me killed.
Okay. By the way, I should just make a brief mention. What
does the מגילה *Megilla* say happens to ושתי *Vashti*?
We all assume—right, she can't be in front of the מלך *melekh*
anymore.
All the מגילה *Megilla* says is, right, אשר לא תבוא ושתי *asher
lo tavo Vashti*, that she's banished. We all—I mean, like, we all
assume, I think it's very rare to find somebody who does not—has
not like inserted the גמרא *Gemara*'s understanding into the מגילה *Megilla* and
realized that ושתי *Vashti* was never killed, at least in the story.
She was banished. Somebody pointed out to me that actually in the
very first ArtScroll מגילה *Megilla*—remember, like going back 30 years before when
they were very small publishing house—and their מגילה *Megilla* was their first
publication, and they actually translated that ושתי *Vashti* should be banished, that
ושתי *Vashti* should not come. You know, as opposed to the way
they translated for example שיר השירים *Shir HaShirim*.
Yes.
In Roman times, to be banished meant that anybody could kill you,
and whoever killed you got your property.
Really? Oh, like the sort of like the גואל הדם ערי מקלט
*goel hadam arei miklat* story. Oh, so maybe that's—maybe that's also—so maybe
it is close to פשט *peshat*. Okay. Let's just turn the page.
ולכולם נתן לאיש חליפות שמלות ולבנימין נתן חמש חליפות שמלות *vekhulam natan
leish chalifot semalot uleBinyamin natan chamesh chalifot semalot*, right? So now we
are going—we'll see obviously how this connects in a minute. So anyway,
this is יוסף *Yosef*, he gave them changes of clothes, and to
בנימין *Binyamin* five changes. אפשר דבר שנתצטער בו אותו צדיק *efshar davar
shenitztayer bo oto tzaddik*, the thing that this righteous person יוסף הצדיק
*Yosef HaTzaddik* himself suffered as a result because of the favoritism, יכשל
בו הוא עצמו *yikashel bo hu atzmo*? He himself would repeat the
mistake? דאמר רבא בר מחסיא אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב
*deamar Rava bar Mechasya amar Rav Chama bar Guria amar Rav*: בשביל
משקל שני סלעים מילת *bishvil mishkal shenei selaim milat* because of like
just a little weight of two סלעים *selaim* of מילת *milat* שהוסיף
יעקב ליוסף משאר אחיו *shehosif Yaakov leYosef mishear echav*, it wasn't a
whole multi-colored, you know, cloak, it was a little bit of a
longer hem or something. Because of that, נתגלגל הדבר וירדו אבותינו למצרים
*nisgalgal hadavar veyardu avoteinu leMitzrayim*, it led to the whole exodus, led
to everybody going down to מצרים *Mitzrayim*. So this thing here that
יוסף *Yosef*'s going to make the same mistake? אמר רבי בנימין בר
יפת *amar Rabbi Binyamin bar Yafet*: רמז רמז לו שעתיד בן לצאת
ממנו *remez ramaz lo sheatid ben latzet mimenu*, no, the whole thing
was symbolic. It wasn't to show favoritism. It was to hint that
there would be a descendant of בנימין *Binyamin* שיצא מלפני המלך בחמישה
לבושי מלכות *sheyetzei milifnei hamelekh bechamisha levushei malkhut*, that would come from
before the מלך *melekh* in the five cloaks of royalty. שנאמר *shenemar*—and
that's the five changes of clothes—ומרדכי יצא בלבוש מלכות תכלת וחור *uMordekhai
yatza bilevush malkhut techelet vachur*, what is it? ותכריך בוץ וארגמן ועטרת
זהב גדולה *vetachrikh butz veargaman veateret zahav gedola*, what is it? ועטרת
זהב גדולה ותכריך בוץ וארגמן *veateret zahav gedola vetachrikh butz veargaman*.
So there's five. Okay. So we will have to end here and
we will continue with a little bit of this יוסף *Yosef* digression
when we return.